Haipeng Yu October 2022

CONTACT Information

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests focus on integrating high-dimensional heterogeneous data to advance genetic improvements in agriculture. Particularly, I am interested in accommodating multi-omics data into genetic evaluations of animals and plants using statistical modeling, machine learning, and computational methods. I am also interested in applying computer vision to collect real-time animal activity data and incorporating the sensor data into my research using machine learning and statistical modeling.

EDUCATION

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal and Poultry Sciences - Quantitative Genetics, May 2020

- Dissertation: "Designing and modeling high-throughput phenotyping data in quantitative genetics" [Virginia Tech Libraries]
- Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

M.S., Animal Sciences - Animal Breeding and Genetics, August 2016

- Thesis: "The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle"
- Advisor: Dr. Lauren Hulsman Hanna

Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao, Shandong CHINA

B.S., Veterinary Medicine, July 2013

Professional Positions

Department of Animal Sciences

University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida USA

Assistant Professor of Artificial Intelligence in Animal Omics Sciences 08/2022 - Present

Principal Investigator

FTE: 75% Research & 25% Teaching

Department of Animal Science

Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

Post-doctoral Fellow 05/2022 - 08/2022

Advisors: Drs. Jack Dekkers and Rohan Fernando

Computational Breeding Team

Inari Agriculture, West Lafayette, Indiana USA

Computational Breeding Scientist 02/2022 - 04/2022

Department of Animal Science

Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

Post-doctoral Fellow 08/2020 - 02/2022

Advisors: Drs. Jack Dekkers and Rohan Fernando

Affiliated Positions University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida USA

• University of Florida Genetics Institute Faculty Member 08/2022 - Present

Work Experience Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

• Graduate Research Assistant 08/2018 - 05/2020

• Graduate Teaching Assistant Spring 2019 and Spring 2020

Department of Animal Science

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska USA

• Graduate Research Assistant 08/2016 - 08/2018

Department of Animal Sciences

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

• Graduate Teaching Assistant 08/2015 - 05/2016

• Graduate Research Assistant 01/2015 - 05/2016

Professional society memberships

- American Dairy Science Association. 2021 Present
- American Society of Animal Science. 2017 Present

EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES

Ad Hoc Reviewer

• Number of manuscripts reviewed per journal: BMC Plant Biology (1), Frontiers in Animal Science (1), Journal of Animal Science (6), Scientific Reports (1), The Plant Genome (1)

Preprints

13. Yu H, Fernando RL, and Dekkers JCM. Validation of the linear regression method to evaluate population accuracy and bias of predictions for non-linear models. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2022.10.02. 510518

PEER REVIEWED
JOURNAL ARTICLES

6 first author and 6 co-author

2022

12. de Novais FJ, <u>Yu H</u>, Cesar ASM, Momen M, Poleti MD, Petry B, Mourao GB, de Almeida Regitano LC, Morota G, and Coutinho LL. Multi-omic data integration for the study of production, carcass, and meat quality traits in Nellore cattle. *Frontiers in Genetics*. 13:948240. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2022.948240

2021

- 11. Clevinger EM, Biyashev R, Lerch-Olson E, <u>Yu H</u>, Quigley C, Song Q, Dorrance AE, Robertson AE, Saghai Maroof MA. Identification of Quantitative Disease Resistance Loci towards Four Pythium Species in Soybean. *Frontiers in Plant Science*. 12:644746. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.644746
- 10. Pegolo S, <u>Yu H</u>, Morota G, Bisutti V, Rosa GJM, Bittante G, and Cecchinato A. Structural equation modelling for unravelling the multivariate genomic architecture of milk proteins in dairy cattle. *Journal of Dairy Science*. 104:5705-5718. doi: 10.3168/jds.2020-18321
- 9. Yu H and Morota G. GCA: An R package for genetic connectedness analysis using pedigree and genomic data. BMC Genomics. 22:119. doi: 10.1186/s12864-021-07414-7
- 8. <u>Yu H</u>, Lee K, and Morota G. Forecasting dynamic body weight of non-restrained pigs from images using an RGB-D sensor camera. *Translational Animal Science*. **5**:1-9. doi: 10.1093/tas/txab006
- 7. Momen M, Bhatta M, Hussain W, Yu H, and Morota G. Modeling multiple phenotypes in wheat using data-driven genomic exploratory factor analysis and Bayesian network learning. *Plant Direct.* **00**:e00304. doi: 10.1002/pld3.304

2020

6. Amorim ST, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, de Albuquerque, LG, Pereira, ASC, Baldi F, and Morota G. An assessment of genomic connectedness measures in Nellore cattle. *Journal of Animal Science*. 98:1-12. doi: 10.1093/jas/skaa289

2019

- 5. Yu H, Morota G, Celestino EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, Riley DG, and Hanna LLH. Deciphering cattle temperament measures derived from a four-platform standing scale using genetic factor analytic modeling. Frontiers in Genetics. 11:599. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2020.00599
- 4. Hanna LLH, Hieber JK, <u>Yu H</u>, Celestino Jr EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, and Riley DG. Blood collection has negligible impact on scoring temperament in Angus-based weaned calves. *Livestock Science*. **230**:103835. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103835
- 3. Yu H, Campbell MT, Zhang Q, Walia H, and Morota G. Genomic Bayesian confirmatory factor analysis and Bayesian network to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics. 9:1975-1986. doi: 10.1534/g3.119.400154

2018

 Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Do stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units? *Journal of Animal Science*. 96:4490-4500. doi: 10.1093/jas/sky316

2017

1. Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics. 10:3543-3556. doi: 10.1534/g3.117.300151

PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS 2022

- 3. Yu H, van Milgen J, Knol EF, Fernando RL, and Dekkers JCM. 2022. A bayesian hierarchical model to integrate a mechanistic growth model in genomic prediction. In: *Proceedings*, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]
- 2. Dekkers JCM, Su H, Kramer L, and Yu H. 2022. An approach for the design of breeding programs using genomics. In: *Proceedings, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production*. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]
- 1. Ni Z, Fernando RL, <u>Yu H</u>, Knol EF, Dekkers JCM. 2022. Genomic prediction of longitudinal body weights in pigs using a neural network. In: *Proceedings*, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]

2018

Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. In: *Proceedings*, 11th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. 11:406. February 11-16, Auckland, New Zealand. [PDF]

BIORXIVED
MANUSCRIPTS

1. Campbell M, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, and Morota G. Examining the relationships between phenotypic plasticity and local environments with genomic structural equation models. *bioRxiv*. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.11.873257

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

2022

- 2. Integrating High-dimensional Heterogeneous Omics Data to Advance Animal Agriculture Using Artificial Intelligence. UF/IFAS Artificial Intelligence Summit. University of Florida. June 21.
- 1. Bayesian hierarchical inference to integrate a nutritional growth model into genomic evaluation of pigs. Feed Platform Meeting. Topigs Norsvin. Online. April 21.

CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

2021

7. A Bayesian hierarchical model to integrate growth models into genomic evaluation of pigs. ASAS-CSAS-SSASAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 14-23.

2020

- **6**. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. EAAP Annual Meeting 2020. Online. December 3.
- 5. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. ASAS-CSAS-WSASAS Virtual Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 19-23.

2019

4. Precision agriculture on cattle temperament: Utilizing factor analysis and multi-trait modeling to characterize a four-platform standing scale. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Blacksburg, VA. October 10-11.

2018

3. An assessment of genomic relatedness across management units. ADSA-ASAS 2018 Midwest Meeting. Omaha, NE. March 12-14.

2017

- Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Stanley Stout Livestock Marketing Center, Manhattan, KS. October 18-19.
- 1. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. ASAS-CSAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Baltimore, MD. July 8-12.

Intramural Seminars

2021

• Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 3.

2020

- Animal Breeding and Genetics Graduate Student Organization seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. October 2.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University.
 September 18.
- Ph.D. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. March 18.

2019

- Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. May 21.
- The Reproductive Biology Club. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. April 19.

2018

 Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 28.

2017

- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 14.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics Seminars. Department of Animal Sciences, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. September 29.

2016

• M.S. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal Sciences, North Dakota State University. May 17.

Teaching

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

Guest Instructor

• GWAS Workshop [Slides]

Summer 2019

Graduate Teaching Assistant

• APSC 5984/20816: Complex Trait Genomics [WWW]

Spring 2020

• ALS 3104: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Spring 2019

Tutorials

- Factor Analytic Model [WWW]
- Gaussian Bayesian Network [WWW]
- Structural Equation Model GWAS [WWW]

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA

Guest Instructor

• ASCI 944 / STAT 844 Quantitative Methods for Genomics of Complex Traits Spring 2018 [Slides] [WWW]

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA Graduate Teaching Assistant

• ANSC 357: Animal Genetics

Spring 2016

• AGRI 189: Skills for Academic Success

Fall 2015

RESEARCH SUPPORT

Internal Funding

Launching Innovative Faculty Teams in AI (LIFT AI) - \$24,025.00 UF
 PI: Jeongim Kim September, 2022 - December, 2023
 Proposal: Dissecting genetic controls of plant root and shoot architecture using AI methods
 Role: Co-Principal Investigator

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENTS

R package

• GCA - https://github.com/HaipengU/GCA

PARTICIPATION IN MEETINGS, SYMPOSIUMS, AND WORKSHOPS

2021

• Poultry Breeder's Roundtable & National Swine Improvement Federation Joint Meeting. Marriott St. Louis Grand, St. Louis, MO. November 30 - December 2.

2020

• The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics. Online. November 2-12.

• The Plant and Animal Genome XXVIII Conference. Town and Country Hotel, San Diego, CA. January 11-15. 2015 • NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. North Dakota State University, ND. October 22-23. • Graduate Learning Conference for College Teaching. North Dakota State University, ND. August 17-18. • WERA-1: Beef Cattle Breeding in the Western Region. Miles City, MT. May 19-20. • ADSA-ASAS Midwest Meeting. Des Moines, IA. March 15-18. Honors/ Awards 2020 • The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics US-Based Early Career Researcher Scholarship. Online. November. 2019 • 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July. • Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium Travel Award \$400, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May. • Frank Bain Graduate Student Scholarship \$1,650, North Dakota State University, Spring. 2015

Additional training

2009-2013

2019

• Deep Learning for Computer Vision Workshop, Virginia Tech, VA, September 6.

• Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship, Qingdao Agricultural University, China.

• 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 17-24.

2018

 Programming and Computer Algorithms in Animal Breeding With Focus on Genomic Selection and Single-Step GBLUP, University of Georgia, GA, May 7-25.

2017

- Introduction to Graphical Models With Applications to Quantitative Genetics and Genomics, Iowa State University, IA, June 19-23.
- Software Carpentry Workshop. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, NE, January 5-6.